<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title></title><atom:link href="http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><link>http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io/</link><description></description><pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2014 18:00:00 -0600</pubDate><generator>Wintersmith - https://github.com/jnordberg/wintersmith</generator><language>en</language><item><title>New satellite-linked camera installed at Columbia Glacier</title><link>http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io//glac.io/blog/Columbia-2014-10-14/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2014 18:00:00 -0600</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io//glac.io/blog/Columbia-2014-10-14/</guid><author></author><description>&lt;p&gt;Our colleagues at the USGS Alaska successfully replaced the old time-lapse camera installed at Columbia Glacier this week with our latest designed system. Capturing and transmitting images every 3-hours during daylight, this camera will help to track the movement of Columbia Glacier, which has been in accelerated retreat since the early 1980’s. Near real-time images can be viewed on the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://gadomski.github.io/locations/columbia/realtime-images.html&quot;&gt;Columbia Glacier Real-time Images&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-12&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;thumbnail tight&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io/blog/Columbia-2014-10-14/COLUMBIA_20141014_220000.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Columbia Camera 1, photo 1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    Image of Columbia Glacier taken from the newly installed satellite-linked time-lapse camera. Images are captured every 3-hours during daylight.
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description></item><item><title>Hubbard Glacier Site Maintenance</title><link>http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io//glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2014-09-24/</link><pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2014 18:00:00 -0600</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io//glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2014-09-24/</guid><author></author><description>&lt;p&gt;Sometimes 1-day in Yakutat is all we need to get out to Hubbard Glacier for site maintenance. That’s exactly what Dave Finnegan and I did September 18th, on the tail-end of a week working up in Girdwood, AK testing our newly designed airborne LiDAR system. Arriving mid-day on the 18th, we immediately turned around and boarded a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.alaska-charter.com/&quot;&gt;Yakutat Charter Boat Company&lt;/a&gt; boat piloted by Mark Sappington, and headed to Gilbert Point. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the last visit in May 2014 our team cleared a safer, more stable path to the Gilbert Point station through the thick alders. Returning after the summer already the path is being reclaimed by nature, having grown over significantly. At the site we modified the Terminus Monitoring System’s battery voltage logging, modified the web camera software to transmit images to our new FTP server, and tightened down the myriad of bolts and nuts that inevitably loosen due to high winds buffeting the station. Overall, the station is solid and strong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next we visited the Haenke Island site, which also has held up nicely since the last visit. We made some modifications to the solar radiation sensor, and downloaded images from the Canon time-lapse camera.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-8 col-md-offset-2&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;thumbnail tight&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2014-09-24/hubbard_09_2014_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Gilbert Point 1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    Dave Finnegan (CRREL) modifies internal software at the Gilbert Point station. Credit: Adam LeWinter, CRREL
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-8 col-md-offset-2&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;thumbnail tight&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2014-09-24/hubbard_09_2014_2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Gilbert Point 2&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    Dave Finnegan (CRREL) modifies internal software at the Gilbert Point station. The laser profiler is visible through the enclosure window. Credit: Adam LeWinter, CRREL
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-8 col-md-offset-2&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;thumbnail tight&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2014-09-24/hubbard_09_2014_3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Gilbert Point 3&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    Gilbert Point station with the Hubbard Glacier terminus in the background. Credit: Adam LeWinter, CRREL
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description></item><item><title>Hubbard Glacier Update</title><link>http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io//glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2013-09-16/</link><pubDate>Sun, 15 Sep 2013 18:00:00 -0600</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io//glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2013-09-16/</guid><author></author><description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;gilbert-point&quot;&gt;Gilbert Point&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Automated Laser ranging system at Gilbert Point was replaced in late August with a new updated system.
Researchers from CRREL, The National Snow and Ice Data Center (Boulder, Colorado) and the USGS Alaska Science Center (Anchorage) removed the previous laser scanning system and replaced it with an updated version of the system developed by CRREL.
The previous system was dependent on a high-powered radio link to Haenke Island, which required significant power to operate.
The new system utilizes a low-power two-way Iridium communication system that reduces overall power consumption and allows for increased data acquisition intervals (hourly).
Furthermore, a realtime camera system has been installed at Gilbert Point to collect and transmit visible images every 3 hours and thermal images every 8 hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;haenke-island&quot;&gt;Haenke Island&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The climate station at Haenke Island is damaged beyond repair and is scheduled for replacement.
Inclement weather prohibited the team from replacing the system in August but the team will return in November to bring a new modern station online.
The new system will also operate on the Iridium network versus the previous GOES system.&lt;/p&gt;
</description></item><item><title>Satellite-linked camera installed at Columbia Glacier</title><link>http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io//glac.io/blog/Columbia-2012-02-07/</link><pubDate>Mon, 06 Feb 2012 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io//glac.io/blog/Columbia-2012-02-07/</guid><author></author><description>&lt;p&gt;In the Fall of 2011, researchers from the USGS (Dr. Shad ONeel) and CRREL worked to deploy a realtime Iridium web camera at Columbia Glacier. The camera is focused on the central terminus of Columbia Glacier and captures up to 4 images per day in optimal lighting conditions. The camera operated succesfully until late November when it suffered a power failure. We are currently working on a schedule to make repairs to the camera. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-8 col-md-offset-2&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;thumbnail tight&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io/blog/Columbia-2012-02-07/COL_cam1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Columbia Camera 1, photo 1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    New satellite-linked camera installed at Columbia Glacier. Credit: Shad O’Neel, USGS.
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-8 col-md-offset-2&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;thumbnail tight&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io/blog/Columbia-2012-02-07/COL_cam2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Columbia Camera 2, photo 1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    Tower with Extreme Ice Survey camera and CRREL satellite-linked camera. Credit: Shad O’Neel, USGS.
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-8 col-md-offset-2&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;thumbnail tight&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io/blog/Columbia-2012-02-07/COL_cam3.Jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Columbia Camera 3, photo 1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    Both cameras capture images of the terminus. Credit: Shad O’Neel, USGS.
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-8 col-md-offset-2&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;thumbnail tight&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io/blog/Columbia-2012-02-07/COL_cam4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Columbia Camera 4, photo 1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    The cameras are battery powered, with solar panels for charging. Credit: Shad O’Neel, USGS.
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description></item><item><title>Laser Ranging Update at Gilbert Point</title><link>http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io//glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2012-02-07/</link><pubDate>Mon, 06 Feb 2012 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io//glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2012-02-07/</guid><author></author><description>&lt;p&gt;The Laser ranging system at Gilbert Point is temporarily off-line until further notice. Due to damage which occurred last summer to the power system, a temporary power solution fitted in September has failed. At the current time plans to repair the system are tentative.&lt;/p&gt;
</description></item><item><title>Helheim Glacier climate station and satellite-linked cameras installed</title><link>http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io//glac.io/blog/Helheim-2012-02-07/</link><pubDate>Mon, 06 Feb 2012 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io//glac.io/blog/Helheim-2012-02-07/</guid><author></author><description>&lt;p&gt;In the Fall of 2011, researchers from the University of Maine (Dr. Gordon Hamilton) and CRREL worked to deploy a new automated climate station and two realtime Iridium web cameras at Helheim Glacier. All of these systems were deployed along the southern margin of the glacier to monitor climate, ice and pro-glacial activity. Due to a late deployment schedule a series of technical difficulties prevented the terminus camera from operating correctly. Furthermore, the climte station operated till December but has since become unavailable. Both of these issues will be repaired in the early spring &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-10 col-md-offset-1&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;thumbnail tight&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io/blog/Helheim-2012-02-07/Hel_station_2.Jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Helheim Install 1, photo 1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    New climate station installed on south side of Helheim Glacier, Greenland. Credit: Adam LeWinter, CRREL.
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-10 col-md-offset-1&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;thumbnail tight&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io/blog/Helheim-2012-02-07/Hel_Station.Jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Helheim Install 2, photo 1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    New climate station installed on south side of Helheim Glacier, Greenland. Camera installation visible in background. Credit: Adam LeWinter, CRREL.
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-10 col-md-offset-1&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;thumbnail tight&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io/blog/Helheim-2012-02-07/Iridiumcam3_2.Jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Helheim Install 3, photo 1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    Iridium-linked time-lapse camera focused on Helheim Glacier. Credit: Adam LeWinter, CRREL.
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-10 col-md-offset-1&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;thumbnail tight&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io/blog/Helheim-2012-02-07/Iridiumcam2.Jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Helheim Install 4, photo 1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    Time-lapse camera focused on the Helheim Glacier terminus, transmitting images daily. Credit: Adam LeWinter, CRREL.
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-10 col-md-offset-1&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;thumbnail tight&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io/blog/Helheim-2012-02-07/iridiumcam3.Jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Helheim Install 5, photo 1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    Time-lapse camera focused on the Helheim Glacier terminus, transmitting images daily. Credit: Adam LeWinter, CRREL.
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description></item><item><title>2011 Summer Activities at Hubbard Glacier</title><link>http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io//glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2011-08-28/</link><pubDate>Sat, 27  Aug 2011 18:00:00 -0600</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io//glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2011-08-28/</guid><author></author><description>&lt;p&gt;As the summer season comes to an end and the Hubbard Glacier terminus has begun its seasonal retreat, we are busy putting the finishing touches on an exciting season of activity. Hubbard advanced to within 70 m of Gilbert Point in July and showed signs of a more advanced position within Disenchantment Bay and Russell Fjord than in previous years.  In terms of a closure, the advanced position of the glacier around Gilbert Point indicates that if a closure is to occur in the future the mechanism will be significantly different than previous closures (1986, 2002).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Researchers from CRREL, University of Maine, University of Kansas and the USGS Alaska Science Center have been monitoring the progress of Hubbard Glacier throughout the summer. In addition to the long-term monitoring systems activities included site visits to the glacier terminus, acquisition of high-resolution satellite imagery, seismic monitoring and on-ice GPS deployment to monitor ice seasonal ice velocities. We will continue to monitor the terminus dynamics at Gilbert Point as funding sources allow us to maintain the infrastructure as necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;monitoring-systems&quot;&gt;MONITORING SYSTEMS&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;gilbert-point&quot;&gt;Gilbert Point&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The monitoring systems at Gilbert Point and Haenke Island have been running continuously since the fall of 2007. The laser ranging system at Gilbert Point operated flawlessly throughout the summer 2011 season until early August after the terminus began to retreat from Gilbert Point. At this point the power system began to fail and data became unreliable until ultimately the power failed completely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;haenke-island&quot;&gt;Haenke Island&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Haenke Island also operated well throughout the season but did sustain some damage over the season. The wind power generation system was damaged in a high wind event and was removed until repairs could be made. The air temperature sensor also suffered a failure early in the season.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;planned-maintenance&quot;&gt;Planned Maintenance&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A maintenance trip is planned for the week of September 5th to repair both stations and make any necessary upgrades to bring the systems back to operational status.&lt;/p&gt;
</description></item><item><title>Potential Closure Update</title><link>http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io//glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2011-06-29/</link><pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2011 18:00:00 -0600</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io//glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2011-06-29/</guid><author></author><description>&lt;p&gt;As sure as the seasons come and go Hubbard Glacier continues its advance towards Gilbert Point. After last years rather quiet season of activity Hubbard has advanced to within 100 meters of Gilbert point. Researchers at USACE CRREL, USGS and the University fo Maine are keeping a watchful eye on its activities. The photos below were taken on June 27, 2011 by CRREL (Dan Lawson). The ice face remains tall and near vertical across most of the terminus. The ice is wrapping itself around Gilbert Point in Russell Fiord and Disenchantment Bay, but the gap at the narrowest point is still about 75 to 80 m off the bedrock face. The ice near the shoal in Disenchantment Bay is being diverted to the east of it and toward Gilbert Point, creating the snout apparent in the image from the Disenchantment side of the channel. The ice face appears in many ways similar to 2009 but possibly with more ice encroaching on the shore at the head of Russell and Disenchantment Bay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our impression is that the glacier remains active in its seasonal advance but prediction of a closure occuring this season is still in question. Stay tuned for more information to come as information relating to Hubbard Glaciers activities is accumulated. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-8 col-md-offset-2&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;thumbnail tight&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2011-06-29/Hub_6272011.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Potential closure 1, photo 1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    Gap between terminus and Gilbert Point. Credit: Dan Lawson, CRREL.
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-8 col-md-offset-2&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;thumbnail tight&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2011-06-29/Hub_6272011_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Potential closure 2, photo 1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    Hubbard Glacier and Disenchantment Bay. Credit: Dan Lawson, CRREL.
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-8 col-md-offset-2&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;thumbnail tight&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2011-06-29/Hub_6272011_3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Potential closure 3, photo 1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    Hubbard Glacier wraps around Gilbert Point. Credit: Dan Lawson, CRREL.
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-8 col-md-offset-2&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;thumbnail tight&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2011-06-29/Hub_6272011_4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Potential closure 4, photo 1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    Hubbard Glacier wraps around Gilbert Point. Credit: Dan Lawson, CRREL.
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-8 col-md-offset-2&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;thumbnail tight&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2011-06-29/Hub_6272011_2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Potential closure 5, photo 1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    Hubbard Glacier wraps around Gilbert Point. Credit: Dan Lawson, CRREL.
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description></item><item><title>Multi-Institute Monitoring of Hubbard Glacier</title><link>http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io//glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2010-05/</link><pubDate>Fri, 30 Apr 2010 18:00:00 -0600</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io//glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2010-05/</guid><author></author><description>&lt;p&gt;Researchers from the US Army Cold Regions Research and Engineering Lab, The University of Maine, the USGS Alaska Science Center and The University of Kansas visited Hubbard Glacier to conduct a campaign to monitor short and long duration glacier activity. These activities included deployment of on-ice GPS for monitoring short term (2-weeks) and long-term (seasonal) glacier velocities. The installation of a new GPS and seismic monitoring station at Haenke Island and new time-lapse and climate monitoring stations in the upper reaches of the glacier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-8 col-md-offset-2&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;thumbnail tight&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2010-05/Haenke_GPSBase.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Haenke GPS Base, photo 1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    Long-term monitoring GPS base station on Haenke Island. Credit: Dave Finnegan, CRREL.
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-8 col-md-offset-2&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;thumbnail tight&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2010-05/Haenke_GPSBase2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Haenke GPS Base 2, photo 1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    Long-term monitoring equipment on Haenke Island. Credit: Dave Finnegan, CRREL.
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-8 col-md-offset-2&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;thumbnail tight&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2010-05/Upper_timelapse_July2010.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Upper timelapse, photo 1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    Image from a time-lapse camera installed on the upper reaches of Hubbard Glacier.
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description></item><item><title>Upper Hubbard Glacier Tributaries Surging</title><link>http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io//glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2009-07-22/</link><pubDate>Tue, 21 Jul 2009 18:00:00 -0600</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io//glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2009-07-22/</guid><author></author><description>&lt;p&gt;Dr Luke Copeland, University of Ottawa has provided the following info about three tributaries glaciers that feed into Hubbard Glacier that are currently surging. The surges are centered around Mt. Queen Mary (60 33’N, 139 50’W), and are in three parallel valleys. Local pilots reported these surges this winter (around Jan-Mar). There is significant crevassing, surface drawdown and strand lines. The terminus of Hubbard glacier was significantly advanced this year in comparison to the last three years of measurement and to date continues to show continued activity but slightly back from it’s seasonal maximum. For information about the surges please contact Dr. Luke Copeland at the University of Ottawa or visit the contact links of this website.
&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-8 col-md-offset-2&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;thumbnail tight&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2009-07-22/allsurge.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;allsurge, photo 1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    Credit: Lance Goodwin, Icefield Discovery.
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-8 col-md-offset-2&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;thumbnail tight&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2009-07-22/centralsurge.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;centralsurge, photo 1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    Credit: Lance Goodwin, Icefield Discovery.
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-8 col-md-offset-2&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;thumbnail tight&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2009-07-22/allsurge2.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;allsurge2, photo 1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    Credit: Pat Leclair, University of Ottawa.
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-8 col-md-offset-2&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;thumbnail tight&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2009-07-22/centernorthsurge.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;centernorthsurge, photo 1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    Credit: Pat Leclair, University of Ottawa.
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-8 col-md-offset-2&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;thumbnail tight&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2009-07-22/allsurge3.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;allsurge3, photo 1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    Credit: Pat Leclair, University of Ottawa.
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-8 col-md-offset-2&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;thumbnail tight&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2009-07-22/centernorthsurge2.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;centernorthsurge2, photo 1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    Credit: Lance Goodwin, Icefield Discovery.
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-8 col-md-offset-2&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;thumbnail tight&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2009-07-22/northsurge.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;northsurge, photo 1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
    Credit: Pat Leclair, University of Ottawa.
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description></item><item><title>Advance of Hubbard Glacier</title><link>http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io//glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2009-06-23/</link><pubDate>Mon, 22 Jun 2009 18:00:00 -0600</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io//glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2009-06-23/</guid><author></author><description>&lt;p&gt;Photos of the Hubbard Glacier terminus. The glacier is wrapping around Gilbert Point. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-8 col-md-offset-2&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;thumbnail tight&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2009-06-23/hubbard_20090623_2.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Hubbard wrap 1, photo 1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      Gap between Hubbard Glacier and Gilbert Point, June 23, 2009.
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-8 col-md-offset-2&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;thumbnail tight&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2009-06-23/hubbard_20090623_1.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Hubbard wrap 2, photo 1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      Gap between Hubbard Glacier and Gilbert Point, June 23, 2009.
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description></item><item><title>Installation of satellite-linked camera at Gilbert Point</title><link>http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io//glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2009-05/</link><pubDate>Thu, 30 Apr 2009 18:00:00 -0600</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io//glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2009-05/</guid><author></author><description>&lt;p&gt;Researchers from the US Army Cold Regions Research and Engineering Lab visited Hubbard Glacier to conduct routine maintenance to the climate monitoring station at Haenke Island and the laser ranging system at Gilbert Point. In addition, several new pieces of equipment were installed to help monitor climate and glacier advance activity. A near real-time low-resolution satellite camera that acquires 3 images per day (1000, 1200 and 1400) was installed at Gilbert Point. The camera is directed 90 degrees to the west of where the laser ranging system is pointed, as to observe advancing activity that has been of interest since the summer of 2008. In addition, a second mechanical wind sensor was installed on Haenke Island for comparison measurements to an existing ultrasonic wind sensor that was thought to be malfunctioning. Both sensors seem to be operating normally. At the current time there is no rain gage installed at Haenke Island due to a malfunctioning switch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-12&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;thumbnail tight&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2009-05/GeoEye_location_map2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;GeoEye Image, photo 1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      Satellite-linked camera and laser profiler fields-of-view as seen on a satellite image from October 25, 2008. Sample images from the satellite-linked camera.
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description></item><item><title>Bathymetric mapping and LiDAR topography survey at Hubbard Glacier</title><link>http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io//glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2008-10-21/</link><pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2008 18:00:00 -0600</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io//glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2008-10-21/</guid><author></author><description>&lt;p&gt;Researchers from CRREL and the US Army Corps of Engineers Coastal Hydraulics Lab in Vicksburg, MS visited Yakutat and the Hubbard Glacier to conduct a complete bathymetric mapping and LiDAR topography survey of the Gilbert Point terminus area. The work utilized an advanced Multi-beam Bathymetric mapping system, a precision 2-D current profiler and a long range ground-based LiDAR scanner all tied together to simultaneously map the submarine environment and tidewater glacier terminus. These data will provide a precision base map that will serve as a spring board for future oceanographic, marine geophysics and monitoring efforts. These efforts were funded by the USACE Alaska District. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-8 col-md-offset-2&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;thumbnail tight&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2008-10-21/GLACIERFACE_FORWEB.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Glacier Face, photo 1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      Hubbard calving face during bathymetric mapping and LiDAR survey. Credit: Dave Finnegan, CRREL.
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-8 col-md-offset-2&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;thumbnail tight&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2008-10-21/RIEGLGLACIERFACE_FORWEB.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Riegl scanner and calving face, photo 1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      Mobile LiDAR system surveying the Hubbard Glacier terminus. Credit: Dave Finnegan, CRREL.
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description></item><item><title>Successful site revisit at Gilbert Point and Haenke Island</title><link>http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io//glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2008-09/</link><pubDate>Sun, 31  Aug 2008 18:00:00 -0600</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io//glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2008-09/</guid><author></author><description>&lt;p&gt; A group of researchers from CRREL and the US Army COE New England District visited the monitoring sites at Gilbert Point and Haenke Island to service all monitoring equipment and download high-resolution imagery collected hourly over the summer. All equipment at both locations was in top working order and no major repairs were needed at this time. The sites are showing signs of wear and next Spring some repairs to the towers and cables will be made to make sure no major problems incur.&lt;/p&gt;
</description></item><item><title>Spring Is Coming</title><link>http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io//glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2008-03-13/</link><pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2008 18:00:00 -0600</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io//glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2008-03-13/</guid><author></author><description>&lt;p&gt;Spring is finally nearing and it looks as if the monitoring equipment at Hubbard Glacier and Haenke Island survived the long cold winter.
Our upgrades to the power systems last season worked as we hoped they would and power was never an issue, even during the darkest months.
The glacier terminus near Gilbert Point should be at a point where it is advancing and we hope the laser ranging unit will begin to return valid data very soon.
Measurements are begining to appear but difficult to determine if the measurements are valid or not.
The laser ranging unit is only capable of about 1000 m range in good conditions.
A team of researchers from CRREL, the New England Corps of Engineers and the Alaska District COE will return in late April to install an updated laser ranging system and a new high resolution imaging camera, which is a joint effort between our research team and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.extremeicesurvey.org/&quot;&gt;Extreme Ice Survey&lt;/a&gt; organization, an effort spear headed by James Balog and National Geographic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-6 col-md-offset-3&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;thumbnail tight&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2008-03-13/HUB_SYSTEM_redux.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Hubbard System, photo 1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      C. Grove USFS
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-6 col-md-offset-3&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;thumbnail tight&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2008-03-13/HUBBARD2_FEB2008_redux.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Hubbard System, photo 2&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      C. Grove USFS
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-6 col-md-offset-3&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;thumbnail tight&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2008-03-13/HUBBARD_FEB2008_redux.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Hubbard System, photo 3&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      C. Grove USFS 
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description></item><item><title>Gilbert Point site maintenance trip</title><link>http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io//glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2007-09-25/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Sep 2007 18:00:00 -0600</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io//glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2007-09-25/</guid><author></author><description>&lt;p&gt; During the Week of September 22nd maintenance visits were made to the Gilbert point ice monitoring system and the Haenke Island meteorological station. Team members included individuals from CRREL, the New England District COE, and the Alaska District COE office in Anchorage, the Geophysical Institute at the University of Alaska Fairbanks and a film crew for The History Channel. No significant modifications or upgrades were made outside of standard maintenance to ensure proper functionality through the winter months. Both sites were in good operating order except for minor bear damage to a solar panel at Gilbert Point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-8 col-md-offset-2&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;thumbnail tight&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2007-09-25/GILBERTPT_SEP07.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Gilbert Point, photo 1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      Regular maintenance of the Gilbert Point monitoring site, September 2007. Credit: Dave Finnegan, CRREL.
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-8 col-md-offset-2&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;thumbnail tight&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2007-09-25/GILBERTPT_CALVE.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Gilbert Point Calving, photo 1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      Calving event in the background during regular maintenance of the Gilbert Point monitoring site, September 2007. Credit: Dave Finnegan, CRREL.
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt; In addition to site maintenance, a bathymetric survey was acquired in the vicinity of Gilbert Point by the Geophysical Institute, UAF the Army Corps of Engineers, Alaska District and CRREL to assess the overall bed conditions in relation to the ice marginal sediment seen during the late summer. At the current time, the ice margin has retreated from its previous position and it remains to be seen if bed conditions will have any influence on a potential closure in the spring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-8 col-md-offset-2&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;thumbnail tight&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2007-09-25/HUBBARD_AERIAL_OCT06.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Hubbard Aerial October 2006, photo 1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      Aerial photograph of the gap between Hubbard Glacier and Gilbert Point.
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-8 col-md-offset-2&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;thumbnail tight&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2007-09-25/HUBBARD_GAP_OCT07.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Hubbard Gap Oct 2007, photo 1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      Calving event in the background during regular maintenance of the Gilbert Point monitoring site, September 2007. Credit: Dave Finnegan, CRREL.
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description></item><item><title>Sediment visible at Hubbard Glacier terminus</title><link>http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io//glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2007-09-09/</link><pubDate>Sat, 08 Sep 2007 18:00:00 -0600</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io//glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2007-09-09/</guid><author></author><description>&lt;p&gt;USACE personnel were recently notified by local boat captain Mark Sappington of sediment above the low tide limit in front of the tidewater terminus in the region between Disenchantment Bay and Russell Fjord. A reconnaissance flight of the glacier conducted on August 31, 2007 with local US Forest Service personnel confirmed this observation. A low, broad mound of sediment was visible above tidewater along one portion of its terminus (see Photo). Upon analysis of oblique aerial photos taken through te course of the summer season and discussions with glaciologist from CRREL the likely source of the sediments has been identified as a preferential subglacial water outlet discharging at the terminus margin. These outlets are capable of depositing large amounts of sedimentary materials and remain active throughout the summer melt seasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Continued monitoring of the terminus of Hubbard Glacier indicates that the glacier is currently in a temporary period of retreat. Even though the glacier is considered to be advancing, the well documented tidewater glacier cycle has shown that they typically advance from mid winter to late spring and typically retreat to a stable position during the late summer to early winter. According to the monitoring data, Hubbard Glacier has retreated a total of 70 m during the month of August leaving the gap 310 meters wide between Disenchantment Bay and Russell Fjord on August 31, 2007.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During this current period of retreat, the sediment observed appears to pose no immediate threat of closing the gap between Disenchantment Bay and Russell Fjord. The continued build up of material in front of the glacier could have consequences once the glacier begins its annual period of advancement. USACE personnel, along with personnel from CRREL and the University of Alaska Fairbanks, are planning to perform further monitoring and data collection efforts to determine the potential implications if sediment remains to build. Available satellite imagery, aerial photos from future reconnaissance flights, and the terminus monitoring data will be analyzed to document changes in the sediment and the position of the glacier terminus. A site visit scheduled for October will allow better assessment of sediments as well as water depths in the surrounding area. After the analysis of data collected during this site visit, a reassessment of the potential effects of the sediment on closure of the gap between Disenchantment Bay and Russell Fjord will be made. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-10 col-md-offset-1&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;thumbnail tight&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2007-09-09/HUBBARD_SEDIMENT_AUG_2007.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Hubbard Sediment, photo 1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      Sediment visible above low tide in front of Hubbard Glacier. Credit: G Kalli, USACE.
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description></item><item><title>Hubbard Glacier site maintenance visits</title><link>http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io//glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2007-05-14/</link><pubDate>Sun, 13 May 2007 18:00:00 -0600</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io//glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2007-05-14/</guid><author></author><description>&lt;p&gt; On May 8th maintenance visits were made to the Gilbert point and Haenke Island monitoring systems. Team members included individuals from CRREL, the New England District COE, the Alaska District COE office in Anchorage and National Geographic. At Gilbert Pt. programming modifications were made to the ranging system to allow for increased data measurements and other necessary refinements. At the Haenke Island Climate site, solar radiation and barometric pressure sensors were added. Additional solar panels were added to both locations. The system is currently functioning and data are flowing from the field to the database as hoped. DCF &lt;/p&gt;
</description></item><item><title>Terminus Monitoring System Installed</title><link>http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io//glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2006-09-29/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Sep 2006 18:00:00 -0600</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io//glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2006-09-29/</guid><author></author><description>&lt;p&gt; Installation of the terminus monitoring system at Gilbert point and the climate monitoring site/radio repeater station at Haenke Island. Installation team consisted of CRREL, New England District and Alaska District COE team members. Installation at each site was successful but due to radio equipment failures in the field. Terminus data acquired failed to relay to the satellite system for transmission to the database. At this time only climate data from Haenke Island is available via the web. A tentative trip is scheduled for November to remediate the problem prior to winter.&lt;/p&gt;
</description></item><item><title>December 2006 Site Visit</title><link>http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io//glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2006-12-04/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Sep 2006 18:00:00 -0600</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io//glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2006-12-04/</guid><author></author><description>&lt;p&gt; A second site visit to Haenke Island and Gilbert point made on December 2nd and 3rd, 2006 for installation of a higher powered radio system and other minor maintenance. The installation team consisted of CRREL, USACE Alaska District and University of Maryland team members. Installation at each site was successful and radio communications between Gilbert Point and Haenke Island are now working properly. Currently, battery voltage and laser range measurements are flowing into the database from Gilbert Point. Because of reflection and return problems with the laser from the ice distance measurements at the current time are sporadic but we anticipate a correction to this soon. The photos below highlight both sites and the current equipment installed at each.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-6 col-md-offset-3&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;thumbnail tight&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2006-12-04/gilbertpt.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Gilbert Point Image 1, photo 1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      Gilbert Point system. Credit: Dave Finnegan, CRREL.
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-6 col-md-offset-3&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;thumbnail tight&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2006-12-04/gilbertpt2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Gilbert Point Image 2, photo 1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      Gilbert Point system. Credit: Dave Finnegan, CRREL.
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-6 col-md-offset-3&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;thumbnail tight&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2006-12-04/haenke_repeater.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Haenke repeater, photo 1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      Haenke Island system. Credit: Dave Finnegan, CRREL.
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;col-md-6 col-md-offset-3&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;thumbnail tight&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;http://gadomski.github.io/glac.io/blog/Hubbard-2006-12-04/haenkesite.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Haenke site, photo 1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
      Haenke Island system. Credit: Dave Finnegan, CRREL.
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>